INSTRUCTOR: Hello, everyone.
Welcome back.
In today's lecture, we are going to talk
about statistics for data exploration and analytics.
Let's begin with a simple question.
What is statistics?
Formally, statistics is a branch of mathematics focused
on collecting, analyzing, interpreting,
and presenting data to extract insights and support
better decisions.
In this lecture, we'll focus on descriptive statistics, methods
that help us summarize and visualize data
to reveal patterns and trends.
Let's start with an example.
Suppose we want to study the heights of students
enrolled at Universal AI.
Instead of measuring the heights of every single student at UAI,
we take a sample--
for example, 100 randomly selected students.
This gives us a data set of 100 height values.
Now we can begin to visualize this data,
for instance, by plotting the heights of all sampled students
side by side.
Of course, we can sort values to identify
trends, which is that most students are similar in height.
So what's the typical student's height?
There are three common ways to describe that.
We can calculate the arithmetic average height, the mean,
which is 65 inches.
Next, we can find the median, which
represents the middle value when data is sorted.
That is, 50 students are shorter and 50 students
are taller than this value.
And finally, we can also identify the mode, which
is the most frequent value.
We can group these heights into bins of equal size and count
how many students fall into each bin.
This process of counting and binning
is the foundation of a visualization technique
used to explore distributions.
Here we can see where most students' heights are centered
and how they are spread across the range.
A few individuals are relatively tall,
but most heights cluster around the center.
Now, instead of using individual dots,
we can use a bar chart to create a histogram.
A histogram shows how often values occur in each bin,
or in our case, a height range.
This gives us a clear picture of the distribution of our sample,
where most students are and how the rest are spread out.
We can change the bin size--
the integral size-- to see how much
variability is visible in the data.
A smaller bin size shows variations
at a higher granularity, while larger bin sizes
reduce visible detail.
So if the bins are too small, the result
can be noisy, whereas if they are too large,
the distribution can become oversimplified.
We can also present the data using Kernel Density Estimation,
or KDE, which provides a smooth alternative
to the traditional histogram.
Unlike histograms, KDE does not rely on bin sizes
and offers a clearer visualization of the shape
of the data distribution.
Another alternative is a violin plot, which is a mirrored KDE.
It is useful for comparing two distributions,
like the distribution of the heights for male and female
students in our example.
Speaking of data shape, skewness is a useful measure
that captures the asymmetry, or tilt, of a data distribution.
It helps us understand whether the data are biased or at one
side of the distribution.
For example, if the points are evenly
distributed around the center, the data
are symmetrical, showing no skew.
If most data points are clustered toward the left,
with a long tail on the right, we call that a positive skew.
If the most points are clustered toward the right,
with a long tail on the left, that's a negative skew.
In a perfectly symmetrical distribution,
the mean, median, and mode are identical.
However, in asymmetrical or skewed distributions,
these three measures differ.
Let's talk about outliers.
An outlier is an unusually high or low value in our data set.
While, in many cases, outliers are expected,
they can also occur due to an error.
For example, let's say we are conducting
our study on students' heights by asking students
to report their heights, and one of the students
jokingly reports their height as the height of the Eiffel Tower.
Now, when we plot the results, the histogram
might look something like this.
Our mean is now distorted.
It rises to over 190 inches.
This shows how a single outlier can heavily influence the mean.
However, the median remains at about 65 inches,
reflecting the true central tendency of the data.
When we inspect the data set, we see that this extremely high
value is clearly erroneous.
We can safely remove it in order to effectively analyze our data.
This is why it is always important to visually inspect
your data before conducting an analysis or drawing conclusions.
Make sure everything makes sense.
So going back to our descriptive statistics,
the mean is appropriate to use when the data is symmetrical.
The median is particularly useful
when outliers are present, since it
is more robust to extreme values,
like the one we just saw.
Finally, the mode is typically used
in categorical data, where it represents the most frequently
occurring category.
So let's talk about variance and standard deviation.
Variance and standard deviation are the two most common ways
to describe how spread-out values are in a continuous data
set.
Sample variance is the sum of the squared deviations
from the sample mean divided by n minus 1,
where n is the sample size.
The standard deviation is the square root of this variance.
Both of these quantify how much individual values
deviate from the mean.
Why is standard deviation important?
Standard deviation shows how spread-out data points
are around the mean.
It helps us understand the consistency of the data.
Smaller values mean data are tightly clustered,
while larger values indicate greater spread and more
variation.
It shows the average distance of the data point from the mean.
In a normal distribution, something particularly
interesting happens.
About 68% of the data falls within one standard deviation
of the mean--
that is, between the mean minus 1 standard deviation
and the mean plus 1 standard deviation.
Furthermore, if we extend this to the mean minus two
standard deviations and mean plus two standard deviations,
we will include 95% of the sample.
Lastly, when we look at the range from the mean minus three
standard deviations to the mean plus three standard deviations,
the range will include almost all
of the sample, or approximately 99.7%.
This is known as the empirical rule, or the 68-95-99.7 rule,
and it applies only to normal distributions.
Let's also talk about quantiles and percentiles.
Quantiles are values that divide a data set
into equal-sized intervals.
For example, quartiles split the data into four equal parts
so that each part contains approximately the same number
of data points.
Percentiles, on the other hand, refer to the position
of values within a data set.
For example, if we have 100 students,
and we divide them into quartiles,
there will be 25 students in each quartile.
We can then refer to these data points using percentiles,
which represent the rank position
of a value within the data set.
The boxplot is an important visualization tool
because it summarizes five key statistics.
Here we can see the first quartile,
which corresponds to the 25th percentile,
meaning that 25% of the data values fall below this point.
The median, which is the second quartile,
or the 50th percentile, indicates that half the data
falls below that value and half above.
The third quartile, which is the 75th percentile,
meaning that 75% of the data lies below this value and 25%
above.
And as the fourth and fifth key statistic,
we can also see the minimum and the maximum that do not
include outliers on the plot.
So it also helps us visualize the center, spread,
and potential outliers as dots in our data.